Hello, my friends, there are many types of the queue.
We have four different types of thank you.
A simple queue.
The circular queue.
The Priority queue and double and the queue.
We have seen in the previous videos how to implement the queue using the array and the link at less
so in a simple queue.
Insertion takes place at the rear and the removal occurs at the from.
It strictly follows the fee for first in, first out rule.
This is the insertion and this is that deletion.
And we have taken many example about this simple cue, and we have implemented it using arrays and linked
lists.
Now the circle of Q a circular Q is that extended version of a regular Q, where that last element in
the code is connected to the first element, thus forming a circle like structure.
Consider it Q Would that have eight elements here?
One two, three, four, five, six and seven.
And they are added together.
0.7 connected.
Let's take an example about the usage of the circular queue.
The circular queue solves the major limitation of the normal queue in a normal queue after a bit of
insertion and deletion.
There will be none usable, empty space here, and this is zero and one can only be used after resetting
the queue deleting of all elements.
This reduces the actual size of the queue.
Circle Q works by the process of circle or increment example, when we tried to increment the pointer
and we reached the end of the queue, we started from the beginning of the queue.
This is very important note that we are going to work with in the next couple of videos and we are going
to implement the circular Q and see and we are going to implement the circular queue in Java.
Now let's see how this circular queue works.
This is an empty queue.
Empty circular queue.
We have two and this is the front and the rear.
They are pointing to minus one in case of they are empty.
If I added five elements to their queue, then the front will be increased by by one and increasing
that to the first element that have been inserted and the rear will increase to the last element that
have been inserted.
OK.
So this queue contains only five elements and accepts only five elements because its size is five and
we have added five elements.
The front will indicate the first element is inserted and the rear will be inserting, indicating the
element that have been lastly insert.
We have inserted this queue by the by, by the way, by one, two, three, four and five.
So the first one is what the first element is.
One.
Now.
If we need to remove and deck from this circular queue, one and two.
Two elements, the first two elements, because that will remove the top elements, the first elements
that have been added.
So the front will be increased and points to the next of these removed elements that will indicate number
three.
Now, if I added a new element to this queue, this queue will not add it at the rear.
It will add it in there in in this queue, in a circular queue because it is working as a circle.
So where is there is an empty space?
It will add that elements to this empty space.
So the front will keep indicating that three is at the front and rear moves, the then newly created
and newly inserted element.
If I insert a new element call number seven, the front will still indicating number three and the rear
moves towards the newly added.
Element inside the circular circle.
You notice, guys, how the circular Q algorithm and how this data structure works, it's still indicating
two things the front which is added and the recent most recently added element and and sort most old
and the oldest element that have been added and they're here will indicate that last element have been
added to the queue.
So front indicate the first element that been added to this Q and the red indicates the last element
have been added to that Q.
Despite that order, like six, seven, three, four five, this is in a normal queue will indicate
that the front is six and remove if we deck from this since normal queue, it will remove six.
But since we are using a circular queue, if we now make execution of deck, it will remove number three
and give it space for another in queuing.